Resume of MD. SOWKAT HOSSAIN

Present Address: Azam Mention, Soripara, Pahartali-4202, Chattogram, Bangladesh

Mobile No: +88 01911840295 E-mail: sowkat@live.com



CAREER OBJECTIVE

To look for a respectable and challenging job willing to work with dedication and hard work to maintain the Admin/HR/Compliance implement with productively in an organization, developing strong manpower, identifying talent and deploying professional development programs to achieve organizational goals and fulfill employee's needs.

CAREER SUMMARY

MY WORK EXPERIENCE IS OVER 18 YEARS IN LARGE REPUTED GROUP AND MULTINATIONAL COMPANIES: FIELD OF ADMIN, HR; COMPLIANCE/CSR

Presently working as Manager (HR, Admin & Compliance) at **PADMA WEARS LIMITED;** (100% Export Oriented Apparels Manufacturer) Plot # 25, Road # 04, Sector # 01, CEPZ, Chattogram, Bangladesh

MULTIFACETED EXPERIENCE IN THE BUSINESS AREA(S):

RMG (Ready Made Garments), Tent Manufacturer (Sleeping Bag, Bag, Bag Pack); Apparel Accessories Manufacturing Industries in CEPZ, KEPZ, DEPZ, Dhaka, Chattogram; Experience has also Indian's largest construction (SIMPLEX INFRASTRUCTURES LIMITED) companies; Flyover Project work. A large project in Bangladesh's largest flyover, the 11.7-km-long 'Mayor Mohammad Hanif' flyover, connecting Jatrabari-Gulistan and developed by private-public-partnership (PPP) project in Dhaka, Bangladesh

KEY SKILL

General HR, Recruitment/Selection, Compensation/Benefits, Attendance/Leave Management, Factory HR Administration, Training and Development, Legal Compliance/Code of Conduct, Organization Development, ISO, HRIS/HR Management, SAP-V-2 & ERP (online tracking) software knowledge.

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATION

Name of Exam.	Group	Div/Class	Board / University	Year
PGD in Compliance Management (PGDCM)	Compliance	A-	Bangladesh Institute of Human Resource Management	2013
Bachelor of Arts (B.A)	Arts	2 nd	National University	2003

COMPUTER LITERACY

Name of Exam.	Group	Div/Class	Board / University	Year
Diploma in Computer Science	Computer	A+	Janani Computers	2001

Operating Systems : Dos, Windows ME, NT, 2000 server & professional, XP, Vista.

Internet Technologies : Front page, Macromedia Flash, Dream weaver, Outlook Express, Eudora.

Graphics : Adobe Photoshop, Illustrator, Page Maker, Acrobat 6.0

Application Packages : MS Office 2000, 2003, 2007, Office XP

Bangla Software : Prabartan 1.0, Bijoy 2000, Bangla XP, Bijoy Classic 2006

Database Software : Ms Access, Visual FoxPro 5.0, And MS SQL Server 2000 Version: 8.0

Tools : Seagate Crystal Reports

Networking Concept : LAN, WAN, Internet

Hardware & Software : System Assembling, Software installation, Hardware maintenance and Troubleshoot

PROFESSIONAL TRAINING

Benefits for Business and Workers (BBW) : Organized by Impactt Bangladesh (Pvt) Ltd.

Gulshan-1, Dhaka, Bangladesh

WRAP Fire Safety Training : Conducted & Facilitated By- Mr. Saifullah Khawaja, Director,

Worldwide Responsible Accredited Production (WRAP), Dhaka, Bangladesh

Basic Concept of HR : Conducted & Facilitated By- Ms. Parveen S. Huda, Managing Director,

Renaissance Consultants Ltd, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Human Resource Information System : Conducted & Facilitated By- Ms. Parveen S. Huda, Managing Director,

Renaissance Consultants Ltd, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Productivity Improvement Program : Organized By- Ocala Consultant Ltd

BEPZA Training Institute, CEPZ, Chittagong, Bangladesh

Global Organic Textiles Standard (GOTS) and

Organic Content Standard (OCS)

Organized By- Global Sustainable Certification Services (GSCS)

Local Partner of CERES GmbH, Crystal Ball Room, Hotel Agrabad,

Chittagong, Bangladesh

Sustainable Impact Partnership Program

(Social & Environmental)

Organized by HENNES & MAURITZ (H&M)

Meridian Apartment, Flat # I/2 (9th Floor) House # 22, Road # 2,

O.R. Nizam Road, Chittagong, Bangladesh

Fundamentals of Supply Chain Management : Conducted & Facilitated By- Mr. Ferdoush Saleheen,

PhD Candidate (Malaysia), MBA (Australia), MS-SCM (USA) Head of Supply Chain at LG-Butterfly, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Industrial Relations, Collective Bargaining and

Negotiation Techniques (IR, CB, NT)

Conducted & Facilitated By- Mr. Ahmad Sheparuddin,

Executive Director, HR & Admin, PHP Family [Former Training Consultant

European Union & IR, Consultant: BEPZA] HRD Foundation, Chittagong, Bangladesh

Quality Management & Productivity Improvement : Small & Cottage Industries Training Institute (SCITI)

Under Bangladesh Small & Cottage Industries Corporation (BSCIC)

Ministry of Industries, Government of Bangladesh

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Time Management : SIMS Bangladesh.

House#31 (4th Floor), Road#14, Sector#14, Uttara, Dhaka.

Website: www.simsbangladesh.com

Customs- Trade Partnership against Terrorism

(C-TPAT)

SIMS Bangladesh.

House#31 (4th Floor), Road#14, Sector#14, Uttara, Dhaka.

Website: www.simsbangladesh.com

Communication at workplace : Bangladesh Skill Development Institute

House no. 2B, Road no. 12, Mirpur Road, Dhanmondi, Dhaka 1209

Website: www.bsdi-bd.org/

Essential Skills for Team Work : Bangladesh Skill Development Institute

House no. 2B, Road no. 12, Mirpur Road, Dhanmondi, Dhaka 1209

Website: www.bsdi-bd.org/

Rules to get success through (Corporate communication)

: Bangladesh Skill Development Institute

House no. 2B, Road no. 12, Mirpur Road, Dhanmondi, Dhaka 1209

Website: www.bsdi-bd.org/

Words for Sustainable Leadership : Bangladesh Skill Development Institute

House no. 2B, Road no. 12, Mirpur Road, Dhanmondi, Dhaka 1209

Website: www.bsdi-bd.org/

How to make an Effective Performance Appraisal : SIMS Bangladesh.

House#31 (4th Floor), Road#14, Sector#14, Uttara, Dhaka.

Website: www.simsbangladesh.com

JOB EXPERIENCES

Length of Service

Over 18 years. :

Department Admin, HR, Compliance/CSR

Employment and position



Manager (HR, Admin & Compliance)

NATURUB ACCESSORIES BD. (PVT.) LTD.

Plot 55-60, Sector 02, Karnaphuli EPZ (KEPZ) Chittagong, Bangladesh

Head Office: No: 105/1, Modupitiya Road Mahawila,

Panadura, Sri Lanka

Web: https://www.naturub.com/

(Sister Concern of Naturub Group of Companies)

From: 1 January, 2019 to 31 December, 2019



Manager (HR & Admin, Compliance/CSR)

Factory: 1. GOLDEN HORIZON LIMITED Factory: 2. PENINSULA GARMENTS LIMITED

Head Office: CDA Annex Building (2nd Floor),

Chattogram -4000, Bangladesh

(Sister Concern of Sunman Group of Companies) From: 8 August, 2015 to 31 December, 2018



Asst. Manager (HR & Admin)

E_Code: 24252

SIMPLEX INFRASTRUCTURES LIMITED

Project Office: Jatrabari-Gulistan Flyover Project Saidabad, Dhaka-1203, Bangladesh

Delhi Office: Hemkunth Chambers (4th Floor) 89, Nehru Place, New Delhi-110019 Web: www.simplexinfrastructures.com/

From: 1 November, 2010 to 31 July, 2015



Sr. Executive (HR, Compliance)

NORTH POLE (BD) LIMITED

Plot # 22-24, Sector # 4, CEPZ, Bangladesh

Sister Concern of Northpole Limited, Hong Kong) From: 6 January, 2007 to 31 October, 2010



Executive (HR, Admin)

SECTION SEVEN LIMITED

Plot # 21-26 (Part), Sector # 03, Road # 4, CEPZ, Bangladesh

(Sister Concern of Shirt Makers Group)

From: 4 May, 2003 to 31 December, 2006



Executive (Admin)

PACIFIC JEANS LIMITED

Plot # 14-19, Sector # 5, CEPZ, Bangladesh (Sister Concern of Pacific Jeans Group)

From: 6 May, 2001 to 30 April, 2003

Abilities

HR & Compliance:

- Control & monitor employee entire Recruitment, Selection, Placement, manpower management, Compensation/Benefits, Legal Compliance/Code of conduct, HR & Administration, Fire, Health & Safety.
- Maintain records and compile statistical reports concerning personnel-related data such as hires,
- Handling Disciplinary & Grievance, employee relation issues, take care of labor disputes and disciplinary matters as per law and monitor on regular basis BEPZA requirements.
- Prepare and control employee's personal file, Wages & Payroll Administration, worker overtime (OT), HR Automation Software Operation.
- Analysis worker turnover and migration for maintain stability, Generate, stream-lined and maintain all HR
- Encourage and motivating workers for better performance and make them understand about importance of factory's rules and regulations, buyer's COC & Country Law.
- Policy & Procedure Prepare: Able to prepared Company profile & Policy, Security Plan (SCS), Standard Operating system (SOP), Factory Operating Manual (FOM), Quality management procedure (QMP), Social Responsible Management Policy, EHS procedure etc.
- Motivate, counsel the staffs to ensure maximum productivity and profitability of the factory.
- Factory monitoring to ensure the compliance issues moreover to work with the non-conformities of
- Communicating with buyers and 3rd party to arrange audit on schedule period
- Leading ISO ISO 14001:2015 (Environmental management systems), ISO 9001:2015 (Quality management systems).
- Working with Higg Index tools (social & Environmental)
- Conduct for Internal and External audits and work with suppliers on corrective action plan to noncompliance concerns.
- Law Knowledge: Labor & Industrial Law, BEPZA Instruction, ILO Conventions, International Compliance & Ethical Standard.
- Take care promotes the company's Values and Ethics.
- ✓ Process and procedure on ISO certification audit:
 - ◆ ISO 14001:2015 (Environmental Management Systems)
 - ◆ ISO 9001:2015 (Quality Management Systems)

Work Experience with Brands and Certification

Brand: Wal-Mart, H&M, PVH, Target, Columbia, Li & Fung, VF Asia/Koontoor, C &A, JC Penney, Yamaki, Primark, Oshkosh-Carters, Kurabo, Mango, Macy's, Decathlon

Wal-Mart Safety audit: SMV (Training) and SMV (Electrical, Fire, Structural), SEDEX (SMETA), WRAP, BSCI, Accord & Alliance, CTPAT, FCCA, SCS, GSV, Higg index, GOTS (Global Organic Textile Standard), OCS (Organic Cotton Standard)

SGS, ITS, BV, Elevate, OMEGA, SCSAS, QHSE SMART, Aipro Engineering & Consultancy.

Administration:

- Administration functions of the organization with the strategic and operational objectives.
- Monitor day to day administrative issues and implement the administrative policy of the company for better improvements.
- Maintain and control Security, Labor Management, Utility services, Housekeeping, Accommodation, Office equipment's, Canteen, Safety, Program arrangements, Staff activities, expatriate management of the company.
- ✓ Protocol support, Facility security control and Supply Chain Management.
- Communicating and working with insurance (transport and workmen's compensation), various Government's regulatory authorities/office like BSTI, Environmental, Boiler, Factory, BSCIC, Premises, and Trade License, Local Police Station, Fire Station, WASA, Passport and Visa Office, Telephone, BRTC, Bank, Labor Office, Labor Court, Local Influences with Labor Federation etc.

IT (Information Technology):

- Implementation and maintaining HR & ERP, Access Control & Time Management Attendance & Payroll software, Mail Server & Backup Server System, CCTV Camera, Finger Print Machine.
- Taking necessary measure for data backup and data recovery, Installation of setting of new/brand PC along with printer & scanner & reader, converter, card printer solution, networking using LAN etc.
- Implemented LAN (Local Area Network) in the office using software hardware & troubleshooting support etc.

OTHER SKILL

Type Writing Course: The Unique Commercial College

340, Pahartali, Chittagong, Bangladesh Bengali 30, English 40 words per minute

Driving Skills: I have knowledge of Light Motor Drive (Bike and CAR),

Driving License no CG0175993CL0005

BIOGRAPHICAL DATA

01. Name : MD. SOWKAT HOSSAIN

02. Father's Name : Harun Ur Rossid Khan

03. Mother's Name : Beauty Beagum

04. Permanent Address : Vill: - Soripara, P.o: - Pahartali, P. s: - Pahartali-4202,

Dist: - Chattogram, Bangladesh

05. Sex : Male

06. Religion : Islam (Sunni)

07. Nationality : Bangladeshi (By birth)

08. Date of Birth : 1st January 1980

09. Marital Status : Married

10. Language Skill : Bengali, English and Chinese

Signature
Md. Sowkat Hossain

Reference:

Giyas Uddin Ahmed Dy. Managing Director



Republic Insurance Company Limited

Ali Bhaban-7th Floor, Moijheet C/A Dhaka, Bangladesh Mobile No: +88 01711405590

Rohitha Kusumsiri Head of Project Viyellatex Group



Factory Office: Vivellatex Ltd Khairtul, Tongi, Gazipura Gazipur - 1712, Bangladesh Mobile No: +88 01723240089 Rajib Kr. Singha Group Head of HR, Admin & Compliance Habib Group HG Tower, 1182 Jubilee Road,



Chattogram, Bangladesh Mobile No: +88 01712012040

Mohammad Kamruzzaman Head of Audit



Stylex Collection

Sister Concern of TNZ Group House # 175, Lane # 02, Eastern Road, New D.O.H.S <u>Mohakhali</u>, Dhaka- 1206, Bangladesh

Mobile No: +88 01812828332